Finding Aid for Robert C. Stempel papers, 1965-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Robert C. Stempel papers
1965-2007
Stempel, Robert C. (Robert Carl), 1933-2011.
2012040 Aa 2; UAm
Designer and automotive engineer with the General Motors Corporation; he later assumed increasing responsibilities within the company as president and chief operating officer and then chairman and chief executive officer. After leaving GM, he became chairman of Energy Conversion Devices (ECD). The Stempel collection documents his work with GMC and ECD and includes minutes of meetings, company memoranda and correspondence, speeches and other various presentations, publications, and photographs and other visual materials. Portions of the collection relate to other business and public service affiliations.
56 linear feet
1 oversize folders
2 film reels
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by the family of Robert C. Stempel (donor no. 10732 ) and came to the library in February 2012.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research except for files less than twenty years old which are closed to research. These files relate to Stempel's involvement with Energy Conversion Devices and are found in boxes 20-37.
Robert Carl Stempel was born July 15, 1933, in Trenton, N.J. He received a bachelor of science degree in mechanical engineering from Worcester Polytechnic Institute in Massachusetts in 1955. He later earned a master's degree in business administration from Michigan State University in 1970.
In 1958, after serving two years in the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, Stempel joined GM's Oldsmobile Division as a senior detailer in the chassis design department. He later served as senior designer (1962); transmission design engineer (1964); motor engineer (1969); and assistant chief engineer (1972). Stempel was a member of the team that developed the 1966 Toronado, the first modern American front-wheel-drive car. According to a GM biography, Stempel designed the Toronado's front suspension and its engine and transmission mounting system. He also participated in the development of the first catalytic converter.
In 1973 Stempel was appointed special assistant to the president of General Motors. He joined the engineering department of the Chevrolet Division as chief engineer-engines and components in 1974 and was named Chevrolet's director of engineering in 1975.
On November 6, 1978, Mr. Stempel was appointed general manager of the Pontiac Motor Division and elected a vice president of General Motors. In September 1980, he was appointed managing director of Adam Opel AG (the German subsidiary of GM) in the Federal Republic of Germany, with responsibility for European-sourced passenger-car operations. In 1982, he returned to Detroit as General Manager of Chevrolet.
In January 1984, he was promoted to the dual responsibility of Vice President and Group Executive in Charge of the Buick-Oldsmobile-Cadillac group. He was elected to the board of directors (February, 1986). He became president and chief operating officer of General Motors Corporation on September 1, 1987. In August 1990, he became chairman and chief executive officer. He resigned in 1992.
In 1993, Stempel joined Stanford Ovshinsky founder of Energy Conversion Devices (ECD) as an adviser. Stempel was named chairman in 1995. In 1999, ECD partnered with Intel in a joint-venture called Ovonyx which developed nonsilicon-based memory for electronic devices. Subsequently ECD formed joint ventures with Texaco Energy Systems Inc., GE Plastics and Belgium-based N.V. Bekaert S.A.
Stempel retired from ECD in 2007; he died May 7, 2011 in West Palm Beach Florida.
The Robert C. Stempel collection has been arranged into the following series: General Motors Corporation; Energy Conversion Devices; Speeches / Conferences / Presentations; Organizational Affiliations, Responsibilities, and Interests; Background / Personal information; Visual Materials, and Sound Cassettes.
Subjects:
Ovshinsky, Stanford R.; Stempel, Robert C. (Robert Carl), 1933-2011.; Council of Great Lakes Industries.; Energy Conversion Devices, Inc.; General Motors Corporation--Management.Management.; National Commission against Drunk Driving (U.S.); Oakland County Business Roundtable.; United States. Presidential Business Delegation to Asia and the Pacific.; Automobile industry and trade.; Automobiles--Catalytic converters.; Automobiles--Motors--Exhaust gas.; Corporate culture--United States.; Corporate governance--United States.; Corporate meetings--United States.; Electric automobiles.; Energy conversion.
Genre Terms:
CD-ROMs.; Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- General Motors Corporation
  The largest series in the collection relates to Stempel's career with General Motors. This series has been further divided by phases or career moves made by Stempel. These include Various Early Responsibilities (1965-1980); President and Chief Operating Officer (1987-1990); Chairman / Chief Executive Officer (1990-1992); and Later Responsibilities (1992-1999). In addition, there are three subseries, one consisting of the depositions made by Stempel as part of litigation involving General Motors. The other two subseries are a collection of General Motors publications and files of RCS schedules and itineraries. Of interest are files relating to the development of the Toronado and to the company's response to issues of automotive emissions in the 1970s.
  - Various early responsibilities, 1965-1980
    - Toronado
      - Chevrolet Engineering Technical Series, March 31, 1966 (Box 1)
        (regarding the Toronado; the file also contains other Toronado talks and notes)
      - Society of Automotive Engineers talk "The Toronado -- A New Breed", 1960s (Box 1)
      - Queens College, Kingston talk about the Toronado, 1960s (Box 1)
      - Articles in automotive and other publications relating to the Toronado, 1965-1966; 1971 (Box 1)
    - Edward Cole (GM President) emission control planning files, 1969-1971
      (These files were made available to Robert Stempel and became part of his emission control study)
      - California Air Resources Board meeting, March 1970 (Box 1)
      - California Air Resources Board meeting, Edward Cole statement regarding gasoline composition effects on emission control, March 1970 (Box 1)
      - California, letter to auto dealers, March 31, 1970 (Box 1)
      - Catalytic converter approach to exhaust emission control meeting, February 1971 (Box 1)
      - Engine emission control, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
      - External combustion engines, 1969 (Box 1)
      - New York City emission issues, 1970-1973 (Box 1)
      - Phoenix test program, 1970 (Box 1)
      - President's Environmental Council, November 20, 1969 (Box 1)
      - Unleaded fuel -- Reduced octane fuel -- Low compression engines and fuel used, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
      - Volpe (Secretary of Transportation John Volpe), meeting with, March 1970 (Box 1)
    - GM motor engineer / assistant chief engineer / director of engineering files, 1968-1980
      - Exhaust emission data, Oldsmobile Division, 1968-1971 (Box 1)
      - Talk "Automotive Design Projects" at the meeting of the Tri-State Mechanical Engineering Society, January 22, 1969 (Box 1)
      - Pollution miscellaneous, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
      - "Teach-in" Michigan State University, regarding automotive pollution, March 13, 1970 (Box 1)
        (include background information)
      - Oldsmobile emission control material, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
      - Article "The diminishing role of the automobile in air pollution", May 15, 1970 (Box 2)
        (includes related memoranda)
      - Automotive emission talk, research and related material, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
      - "Grass roots" speech, 1972 (Box 2)
        (generic speech information given on the topic of automotive emissions)
      - Oldsmobile Division memoranda, 1972 (Box 2)
      - Oldsmobile 1975-1976: Emission System Evaluation, special chief engineers' meeting, September 1972 (Box 2)
      - Oldsmobile 1975-1976: Engine Control Program Planning, September 1972 (Box 2)
      - Oldsmobile 1975-1976: Engine -- Exhaust emission plans, October 23, 1972 (Box 2)
      - Progress report on automotive air pollution control, 1972 (Box 2)
      - Oldsmobile, Engine displacement program, April 25, 1973 (Box 2)
      - Special Chief Engineers meeting -- catalytic converter presentation, May 29, 1973 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous, 1973 (Box 2)
      - "Fuel Economy Trends and Catalytic Devices" article written by Stempel and Stuart W. Martens from talk at meeting of the Society of Automotive Engineers, 1974 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
      - Penn State University talk "Auto Future -- What's Next?", March 30, 1976 (Box 2)
      - 1976 "The Automotive Future -- What's Next?" 1976 (Honorary Engineering Lecture, Penn State University, published version) (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous, 1976 (Box 2)
      - Senior Management Conference, 1977 (Box 3)
      - 1978 Chevrolet Engineering Management Conference, February 1978 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous, 1977-1978 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous, 1979; 4 folders (Box 3)
      - RCS Executive Report, January 22, 1980; 1 audiocassettes (Box 3)
      - GM Executive Conference, RCS notes, April 1980 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous, 1980 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous incoming mail, 1979-1980 (Box 3)
    - Vice President European Passenger Car Operations, Adam Opel 1980-1982 and General Manager (Chevrolet Division), etc., 1982-1987
      - Adam Opel Engineering reports, business plan (Box 3)
      - Adam Opel organization changes in overseas group, 1981 (Box 3)
      - European market and related (Box 3)
      - Press conferences, European motor press (Box 3)
      - Frankfurt business journalists, RCS notes on, March 30, 1981 (Box 3)
      - Adam Opel Publications (Box 4)
      - GM Quality Network, 1981 (Box 4)
      - GM Executive Conference, RCS notes, February 16, 1981 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Campbell-Ewald advertising for Chevrolet, 1982 (Box 4)
        (include audiocassettes)
      - IBM visit, 1984 (Box 4)
      - Conflict of Interest questionnaire, 1983-1986 (Box 4)
  - President and Chief Operating Officer, 1987-1990
    (includes some earlier material)
    - Directors and Officers Questionnaire, 1982-1989 (Box 4)
      (RCS copy regarding stock ownership, etc.; form was required by the corporation in preparation of its proxy statement prior to the annual meeting)
    - Talk and related, 20th anniversary Safety Research and Development Laboratory, 1988 (Box 4)
    - General Motors Executive Committee, Group Executive Conference, March 30-31, 1988 (Box 4)
    - "Quality Network" Task Group Report August 1988 and related later material, 1993 (Box 4)
    - 1988 correspondence and other papers, January-May 1988, 7 folders (Box 4)
    - Memoranda and other communications from Elmer W. Johnson to the Executive Committee relating to strengthening GM's organizational capability, January 1988 (Box 4)
    - General Motors Product Program Management Process, The Four Phase Process, 1989 (Box 4)
    - 1989 Leadership Conference, 1989 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1989 (Box 4)
    - General Motors Management Team, photograph and press material, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Progression and Succession Reviews, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Memorandum received relating to environmental compliance, April 6, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Letter received relating to the relationship with the UAW, April 18, 1990 (Box 4)
    - General Motors Management Committee booklet, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Labor issues, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Outside board member visits, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1990 (Box 4)
  - Chairman / Chief Executive Officer, 1990-1992
    - Financial Committee and Board of Directors meeting, January 7, 1991 (Box 5)
    - Board of Directors meeting, February 4, 1991 (Box 5)
    - Financial Committee and Board of Directors meeting, April 1991 (Box 5)
    - Financial Committee and Board of Directors meeting, May 6, 1991 (Box 5)
    - Financial Committee and Board of Directors meeting, May 23, 1991 (Box 5)
    - Financial Committee and Board of Directors meeting, July 1, 1991 (Box 5)
    - Financial Committee and Board of Directors meeting, August 5, 1991 (Box 5)
    - Financial Committee and Board of Directors meeting, October 7, 1991 (Box 6)
    - Financial Committee and Board of Directors meeting, November 4, 1991 (Box 6)
    - Financial Committee and Board of Directors meeting, December 9, 1991 (Box 6)
    - Financial Committee and Board of Directors meeting, January 6, 1992 (Box 6)
    - Financial Committee and Board of Directors meeting, February 3, 1992; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Financial Committee and Board of Directors meeting, March 2, 1992 (Box 6)
    - Financial Committee and Board of Directors meeting, April 6, 1992 (Box 6)
    - Board of Directors meeting, May 4, 1992 (Box 7)
    - Board of Directors meeting, May 21, 1992 (Box 7)
    - Board of Directors meeting, June 29, 1992 (Box 7)
    - Board of Directors meeting, August 10, 1992 (Box 7)
    - Board of Directors meeting, September 1992 (Box 7)
    - Board of Directors meeting, October 5, 1992 (Box 7)
      (include papers relating to Executive Committee and visit of Clayton K. Yeutter, counselor to US President George H.W. Bush)
    - Board of Directors meeting, November 2, 1992 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence to/from outside directors for use at board meetings (Box 8)
      (also includes other board materials)
      - August-December 1990, 5 folders (Box 8)
      - 1991, 11 folders (Box 8)
      - January-November 1992, 11 folders (Box 8)
    - Management Committee meetings, 1990-1992 (Box 8)
    - Management Committee strategy issues, 1990-1991 (Box 8)
    - GM Management -- Transition, 1990; 3 folders (Box 9)
      (include transparencies)
    - Directors and Officers Questionnaire, 1990-1992 (Box 9)
    - Outside Directors Discussion, February 1990; 2 copies (Box 9)
    - Director Independence Policy, 1990-1991 (Box 9)
    - Overview: Operating Plan Revisions (presentation to Finance Committee), February 4, 1991 (Box 9)
    - GM Capital Allocation and Related Strategic Considerations, September 1991 (Box 9)
    - Meeting with outside board members, November 3, 1991 (Box 9)
    - Administration Committee, November 21, 1991 (Box 9)
    - Questions (anticipated) for board of directors at meeting of, January 10, 1992; 2 versions (Box 9)
    - Letters addressed to outside board members, 1990-1992 (Box 10)
    - GM Plant Closings (various documentation), 1991-1992 (Box 10)
    - North American Operations Leadership Meeting, October 16, 1992 (Box 10)
    - Combined record volume: include 1992 Progression and Succession Review and Organization Review Presentation, October 1992 (Box 10)
    - GM Corporate Strategy Planning, 1992 (Box 10)
    - GM/Toyota Joint Venture Statement, 1992 (Box 10)
    - John Smale letters, meetings and related materials, 1992; 3 folders (Box 10)
    - Management changes, April 1992 (Box 10)
    - Executive Interview Background Summary (and related material), October 1992 (Box 10)
    - Earning Report (3rd quarter) and Profitability Projection Overview, October 1992 (Box 10)
    - Regarding sale of stock, 1991; 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Notes of visit of R. C. Gerstenberg, June 11, 1992 (Box 11)
    - Memoranda from Alex C. Mair, May 1992 (Box 11)
    - Lloyd E. Reuss material, 1991 (Box 11)
    - International security concerns, 1990-1991 (Box 11)
    - Management Committee, organizational review, 1991 (Box 11)
    - Management Committee, miscellaneous, 1992 (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous, 1991-1992 (Box 11)
  - Later GM Responsibilities (consulting, GM Corporate Advisory Council), 1992-1999
    - , resignation letter and related communications and press releases, October 26, 1992 (Box 11)
    - , letters pertaining to resignation, October-December 1992; 2 folders (Box 11)
    - , regarding hospitalization, October 1992 (Box 11)
    - , press releases, etc., November 1992 (Box 11)
    - , regarding Maryann Keller's book Collision, 1993 (Box 11)
    - , post-resignation clippings, 1993 (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous, 1993; 2 folders (Box 11)
      (include John Smale correspondence)
    - , regarding Paul Ingrassia and Joseph B. White book Comeback; The fall and rise of the American automobile industry, August 1994 (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous, 1994 (Box 11)
  - General Motors litigation / Robert Stempel depositions
    - A-I (Box 12)
    - J-M (Box 13)
    - O-Z (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous depositions and related (Box 14)
    - C/K Truck Product Liability Litigation (Box 15)
  - General Motors Publications
    - 75th Anniversary, 1908-1983 (Box 16)
    - Automotive Engine Test Code (Box 16)
    - Automotive Product Responsibilities (Box 16)
    - Benefits Handbook (Box 16)
    - Cadillac Legacy (Box 16)
    - Changing Challenge, 1974-1975 (Box 16)
    - Chevrolet, '75 Caprice Classic Convertible (Box 16)
    - Chevrolet Engineering Organization (Box 16)
    - Chevrolet Power, 2, 3, 4, Editions (Box 16)
    - Chevy Corvette (Box 16)
    - Chevy Corvette, 1 volumes (Box 16)
    - Chevy El Camino (Box 16)
    - Chevy Racing Engine (Box 16)
    - Corvette, Road & Track Magazine (Box 16)
    - Daytona 500 (Box 16)
    - Electric Vehicles (Box 16)
    - Emissions Control, Progress & Programs in Automotive (Box 17)
    - Emissions Control Systems, September 1972; 1 volumes (Box 17)
    - Emission [Gasoline] Relationships, Progress & Programs in (Box 17)
    - Energy Booklet (Box 17)
    - Energy Situation, 03/15/1975; 1 volumes (Box 17)
    - Environment, GM (Box 17)
    - Environmental Improvement Program (Box 17)
    - Environmental Report (Box 17)
    - Forward Drive: The Race to Build the Car of the Future by Jim Motavalli (Box 17)
    - Guidelines for Employee Conduct (Box 17)
    - Identification Manual, 1 volumes (Box 17)
    - International Quality Study (Box 17)
    - Miscellaneous Brochures, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Motor, Annual Training Issue (Box 17)
    - MVMA Motor Vehicle, Facts & Figures, 1992 (Box 17)
    - Newsletters (Box 17)
    - Opel Junior (Box 17)
    - Pollution (Box 18)
    - Pontiac (Box 18)
    - Power (Box 18)
    - Product Compliance Program, 1 volumes (Box 18)
    - Public Issues, Background Materials on, Affecting GM, 1 volumes (Box 18)
    - Quality (Box 18)
    - Racing (Box 18)
    - Research, Future Emission --Controlled Spark -- Ignition Engines and their Fuels (Box 18)
    - Safety (Box 18)
    - Top Management DFM Orientation Handbook (Box 18)
    - Total Quality Assurance System (Box 18)
    - Executive Conference
      - 1972 (Box 18)
      - 1977 (Box 18)
      - 1980 (Box 18)
      - 1983 (Box 18)
    - Leadership Conference
      - 1988 (Box 18)
      - 1989 (Box 18)
  - Schedules and Itineraries
    - Itineraries, 1986-1996; 11 folders (Box 19)
    - Appointment books for RCS (maintained by Sylvia Drzazdzynski), 1986-1994; 10 volumes (Box 19)
  - Motion pictures
    - "ABCs of Catalytic Converters", 1973; 1 reels
      (reel no. 2)
    - "Olds Division; Air Pollution in Perspective", 1970s; 1 reels
      (reel no. 1)
- Energy Conversion Devices, 1993-2007
  The Energy Conversion Devices details the founding and development of this company through the records of the annual meeting and the board of directors. A significant portion of the files relate to presentation made by Stempel on behalf of the company to various banking and asset management firms. Some of the files relate to Stempel's enthusiasm for electric vehicles. Within this series are compact discs (CD-R) of the power-point presentations made by RCS.
  [RESTRICTED until 20 years from the creation of the record]
  - Meetings (annual, board of directors, audit, other committees) (Box 20)
    - 2003-2007 (Box 20)
    - 2007 (Box 21)
    - 2007 (Box 22)
  - Presentation material for various investment banking and asset management firms (Box 23)
  - Wholly owned subsidiaries of ECD (Box 24)
    - Uni-Solar (United Solar Ovonic) (Box 24)
    - Ovonic Hydrogen Systems (Box 24)
  - Global Automotive Conference -- presentation materials, 2005 (Box 24)
  - Honda's investment in Ovonic Battery Co. (Box 24)
  - Meeting files, 2001-2007 (Box 25)
  - Toyoda NIMH testing (Box 25)
  - Toyoda miscellaneous (Box 25)
  - Proposed photovoltaic manufacturing and assembly plant, Hoyerswerda, Germany, 2005 (Box 25)
  - Electric Drive Transportation Association conferences and board meetings (Box 26)
  - Electric vehicles miscellaneous (Box 26)
  - Presentation materials (Box 27)
    - Ovonic work presentation (Box 27)
    - Investor presentation, 2005 (Box 27)
    - Texaco Ovonic Battery System, 2003; 2 folders (Box 27)
    - Ovonic Solar Presentation (Box 27)
    - Cobasys Investment Banker Package, July 2006 (Box 27)
    - Military Open House, 2003 (Box 27)
    - Cobasys Investor Presentation, July 2006 (Box 27)
    - Organizational Materials, 2005 (Box 27)
  - Electric vehicles (Box 28)
  - Presentation materials (Box 29)
  - Electric vehicles / EVAmerica (Box 30)
  - Electric vehicles (Box 31)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 31)
  - GMOvonic/Ovonic Battery Co., 1997 (Box 32)
  - ECD/Ovonic NiMH Battery (Box 32)
  - ECD/Ovonic Battery and Hydride, 1997-1998 (Box 32)
  - Hybrid-Electric Vehicles, 1996 (Box 32)
  - Various presentations (Box 32)
  - Unprocessed; meetings presentations, etc. (Box 33)
  - Unprocessed; meetings presentations, etc. (Box 34)
    (continued)
  - Power-point presentations (compact discs) given by RCS on behalf of Energy Conversion Devices, 2002-2006; 53 optical disks CDs
    - ETI Conference, Speaker Presentations Supplementary Edition, 2002 (Box 35)
    - Transforming the Future, Manufacturing Technology Development (Box 35)
    - UK-Europe Visit, June 2002 (Box 35)
    - Presentation, Hart, World Fuels Conf., September 27, 2002 (Box 35)
    - Presentation to Clinton River Watershed Council, October 17, 2002 (Box 35)
    - Presentation, Busan, Korea, October 21, 2002 (Box 35)
    - Hydrogen-Fueled Prius, Phase I, Video Status Report, by Dick Geiss, October 2002 (Box 35)
    - Innovan Presentation, Board of Directors Mtg., November 8, 2002 (Box 35)
    - Presentation for EVAA, December 12, 2002 (Box 35)
    - Ward's 10 Best, January 8, 2003 (Box 35)
    - 20th Int'l Seminar & Exhibit on Primary & Secondary Batteries, March 17, 2003 (Box 35)
    - The Ovonic Solid Hydrogen, ICE Vehicle: Ready for a Test Drive, September 18, 2003 (Box 35)
    - IPHE as Facilitator of Hydrogen Stationary Applications, November 19, 2003 (Box 35)
    - IPHE Presentation, November 19, 2003 (Box 35)
    - Ovonics Presentation at Ford, May 18, 2004 (Box 35)
    - Ovonics Presentation to Int'l Joint Commission, June 15, 2004 (Box 35)
    - Presentation to Jefferies, July 19, 2004 (Box 35)
    - Ovonics Germany, October 2004 (Box 35)
    - Presentation, Konrad-Zuse-Stadt Hoyerswerda, November 16, 2004 (Box 35)
    - Investment Incentives in Saxony, November 2004 (Box 35)
    - Automotive News World Congress, "Powertrains of the Future", Panel Discussion, January 18, 2005 (Box 35)
    - Ovonics Presentation at 2005 DTE Energy Conference, February 15, 2005 (Box 35)
    - Presentation at Morgan Stanley Global Automotive Conference, March 22, 2005 (Box 35)
    - RCS Generic Presentation, April 2005 (Box 35)
    - Presentation at the Global Automotive Conference, April 7, 2005 (Box 35)
    - Presentation to First Albany Capital, April 20, 2005 (Box 35)
    - Generic Presentation, June 20, 2005 (Box 35)
    - Ground -- Automotive Power & Energy Symposium, July 21, 2005 (Box 35)
    - Generic Presentation, August 2005 (Box 35)
    - Geely Holdings Group, August 12, 2005 (Box 35)
    - Presentation at SAE North American Int'l Powertrain Conference, September 8, 2005 (Box 35)